There you go.
There. You were hungry.
That's it.
I must essay a path whereby
I, too, may rise from earth and fly
victorious on the lips of men.
I must essay a path whereby...
...victorious on the lips of men.
I must essay a path whereby
I, too, may rise from earth and fly
victorious on the lips of men.
I must essay a path whereby
I, too, may rise from earth and fly
victorious on the lips of men.
I must essay a path whereby
I, too, may rise from earth and fly
victorious on the lips of men.
Repeat.
Good day, sir.
Good day to you.
What brings you to Hewlands?
I'm tutoring the boys here.
The Latin tutor.
I've heard of you.
What brought you into the garden?
Uh...
It's just a question, master tutor.
Yes, I, uh...
I suppose the air was
fresh out here, and...
uh, I saw you with your bird.
- It's a hawk.
- Ah.
May I?
Don't get too close.
He doesn't know you.
Oh.
Hello, boy.
Ah.
He likes you.
What is your name?
I shan't tell you.
You shall.
I shan't.
- You shall.
- I won't.
You'll tell me when we kiss.
What are you doing?
Agnes.
My name is Agnes.
Where are you from?
Have I said something?
- Huh?
- No.
- You don't know who I am.
- Wait, I wish to see...
You can't see me again.
Oh.
Where have you been?
I was in the field helping Bartholomew.
A newborn lamb is unwell.
Well, I... I went to the field.
I did not see you there.
Well, I was there.
Tell her, Bartholomew.
She was there.
Have you seen the new Latin tutor?
The glover's son.
The boys said he just
ran out, never returned.
He was supposed to give them lessons
to pay off his father's debts.
I haven't seen him.
Well, should've known better.
Like father, like son.
You know, I do believe you are
the prettiest girls in the parish.
- We are.
- One day,
I shall have my wits about me
for all the suitors
that will come for you.
Agnes is the eldest.
She'll marry first.
She will not if she keeps
running off to the forest
like a gypsy.
- When they said...
- Where have you been?
We were expecting you hours ago.
- I was...
- Well?
I was working.
Sit.
Your supper's near cold.
- Uh, boys, boys!
- Hey.
- Stop.
- There's enough for all.
How go the lessons at Hewlands?
Those boys are no scholars.
- I wonder at the notion of all that learning.
- Hmm.
Latin for boys who will be
naught but sheep farmers.
- It is the putting on of airs.
- No, no, no!
- That will do!
- All right, Gilbert.
You heard your mother.
There's enough for all.
You speak ill of the boys at Hewlands.
"They're no scholars."
But I tell you something,
they'll ever be more
of a man than you are.
They are put to
honest work, unlike you.
Useless, tradeless, your fancy airs.
All that education,
not an ounce of sense.
I'm tutoring those boys to pay
your debts to that family, am I not?
Your immeasurable amount of debt,
Didn't I help you... Stop!
What of the rest of
the family at Hewlands?
Have you met them?
The mother only.
- Not the eldest daughter?
- No.
It is said the girl is the
child of a forest witch.
I've seen her, wandering
the back roads alone
with a hawk on her arm.
A hawk at Hewlands?
Yes.
They say she takes him to the
forest with her unaccompanied.
Yeah, but are you certain, Eliza?
The eldest daughter keeps
a hawk, not a servant girl?
Yes. Yeah.
Agnes.
Hello.
What are you doing here?
Brought you this.
What is it?
It's, uh...
it's a new glove for your bird.
I have a glove.
Agnes.
Agnes, wait.
I know who you are.
Who am I?
Well, I... I don't know
you, but I've heard things...
I'm the daughter of a forest witch?
Yes. People say
that, but I-I don't care...
I am my mother's daughter.
I've learnt many things from her.
What are you looking at?
- You.
- Why?
- I...
- I thought you were a man of words, master tutor.
Yes.
- Are you not?
- Jus...
Speaking with people is
sometimes difficult for me.
Well, tell me a story, then.
- A story?
- Yes.
What story would you like?
Something that moves you.
All right.
Do you know the story
of Orpheus and Eurydice?
Orpheus is...
a man of music.
He has this exquisite voice.
His playing of the
kithara, which is a...
is-is a harp-like lyre,
is so divine,
birds, the...
the beasts, e-even the
stones and the trees,
they all moved to the
rhythm of his music.
Now, Orpheus falls in love with
this beautiful nymph, Eurydice.
Soon after their marriage,
Eurydice's bitten by a viper
and poison courses through her body,
and she's killed.
And Orpheus, filled with grief,
journeys to the
underworld to take her back.
He charms this
three-headed dog, Cerberus.
He beguiles Hades until finally...
...he's allowed to take
his love back with him
to the world of the living but...
...under one condition.
What is it?
She must follow behind him,
and he must not turn
around to look at her.
Now, as they begin their ascent,
Orpheus can't hear her
footsteps, so he listens...
...and listens and listens and listens.
But all he can hear is
the sound of his heartbeat.
And the rest is silence.
And as he approaches the
gates of the underworld...
...he can't contain himself any longer.
He turns around to
look at her, and she is...
...trapped in the underworld forever.
Hmm.
That was a good story.
Did you like it?
Remember, mugwort,
what you brought to pass,
what you readied at Regenmeld.
You're called Una,
the most ancient plant.
You defy three, you defy 30,
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
you defy the horror
that stalks the land.
And you, waybread, plant mother,
you're open to the
east yet mighty within.
Carts creeped over you,
women rode over you.
You withstood it all,
and you pushed back.
Is it true that you know
everything about a person
by touching them here?
Not everything.
When you touched me
here, what did you see?
I saw a landscape.
- You saw a landscape?
- Mm-hmm.
Spaces, caves, cliff tops,
tunnels and oceans,
this deep, dark, black void,
undiscovered countries.
Thus by law of fate all things
speed towards the worse
and, slipping away, fall back.
Thus by law of fate all things
speed towards the worse
and, slipping away, fall back.
She speaks...
She speaks, she speaks.
But, soft,
what light through
yonder window breaks?
It is the east, and
Juliet is the sun...
...and kill...
...the envious moon.
Hello.
I wish to be handfasted to you.
No, I... I must be handfasted to you.
No one else will do.
I-I will speak with your
stepmother and your brother,
and of course they
will not agree, but...
I don't care because I
have no talent for waiting.
I cannot abide waiting.
What about your parents?
Your parents will never agree.
Follow me.
Wait. Wait. W-Wait.
- No!
My glove.
- This is my mother's glove.
- Hmm.
She came out of the woods...
...like her mother
and her mother before her.
The women in my family see things...
...that others don't.
Agnes.
Remember, mugwort,
what you brought to pass,
what you readied at Regenmeld.
You're called Una,
the most ancient plant.
You defy three, you defy 30,
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
you defy the horror
that stalks the land.
Bartholomew, it will heal.
Will it make a scar?
It may. That's no bad thing.
Listen.
Do you hear that?
You must pay attention
to your dreams, Agnes.
They will always guide you.
- Good day.
Yes.
Agnes, what's, uh...
what's happened?
Her mother has banished
her from their house.
She's not my mother.
The house belongs to
my brother, Bartholomew.
I chose to leave.
She's with child.
Oh.
Says it's yours.
- Is it? Yours?
- Uh...
The child in her belly,
did you put it there?
I did.
- We are handfasted, Mother.
- We will never allow it!
- There is no sin in it.
- I'm afraid you will need
- our consent, and we will...
- There is no sin in it!
- ...we will never give it, ever!
- All right!
What?
- You've been bewitched.
- No.
I'd rather you went to
sea than marry this wench.
Mary.
There's no need for that.
I have no doubt we can
come to an arrangement.
- John.
- Hush, woman.
I am certain you are eager
to see your sister before the altar.
I'm certain you'd
rather not see your boy
dragged before the bawdy court.
There's no need for that.
They said they are handfasted.
Only if I say so.
But why marry a pasty-faced
scholar? What use is he?
He's got more inside of him
than any man I've ever met.
Everything will change.
You. You will change.
I'm already changing.
It's too quiet in there.
In where?
That house.
What would our mother say to
us if we were afraid or uncertain?
To live with our hearts open.
To shut it not in the dark
but to turn it to the sun.
He loves me for what I
am, not what I ought to be.
Then marry him you shall.
Thank you.
Remember, mugwort...
Say it with me. Say it with me.
What you brought to pass,
what you readied at Regenmeld.
You are called Una,
the most ancient plant.
You defy three, you defy 30,
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
you defy the horror
that stalks the land.
Look at me.
Agnes.
Hey.
Look. Look at that. Look at the fire.
Mmm, what's that?
The doggy dragged something in.
There's something.
Oh.
Daddy's coming.
Hello.
Stitches need to be smaller.
M-Much smaller.
Yes.
Hmm.
Useless.
Okay, and now...
smaller.
- Where are you going?
- I'm going.
Get back to work.
That was the last time
you will ever hit me.
Do you understand?
- Do you understand?!
- Yes.
My love, you should come back to bed.
What are you writing?
Nothing of note.
It's never nothing.
I don't know.
Perhaps when it's finished, it will...
Perhaps when it's finished.
Why don't you read
me what you've written?
A-Agnes, it's not--
It-It's not finished.
It's not finished.
Stop it. You'll wake the baby.
It's okay.
No. It's okay.
I'm sorry.
I've had too much, uh...
Agnes, I've had too much to drink.
I've had...
I've had too much to drink.
Hey.
What is it?
Give me your hand.
Pl-Pl-Please, please, please, please,
please, please, please, please.
- What are you afraid I will see?
- Please stop.
That I am a violent and dangerous man.
No, you are none of those things.
- How do you know?
- You're a good man. You're a...
You are a good man.
You're a good man.
Is it that you wish that we never wed?
How could you say such a thing?
You and Susanna
are all that I live for.
All that I live for.
- What is it, then?
- This...
- Here. Look at me.
- Just stop!
Stop, stop. Please, please,
please, please, please, please.
Look at me.
Listen. Listen. Listen.
I'm lost.
I've lost my...
I've lost my way.
I just need to-- uh,
Agnes, I just need to work.
He's not sleeping.
- Has he ever lost his temper with you?
- No.
- If he raises a hand...
- No, he has never. He's never.
He's angry with himself.
He's sick with himself.
He's a good man.
He's a good husband,
he's a good father,
but he n-needs more.
What could he possibly need
other than his family and you?
- He has you.
- He needs to go to London.
- London?
- Yeah.
Why London?
Because London is where
the whole world gathers.
Perhaps he could extend
his father's business there.
- Oh, you're being hasty again.
- Who knows what he may be...
I'm not being hasty. He needs more.
- Well, he needs proper work.
- He's not of this world.
The man needs proper work.
- What's in this little town?
- He can't just run away.
This little life?
This little thing, it'll...
...crush him.
He needs distance from his father.
And you would go with him to London?
No, I'll wait until he's settled.
There'll be more of us soon.
- Another child?
- Yes.
By summer's end.
Then now is not the
time to send him away.
I'll lose him.
I'm already losing him.
You'll lose him if you send him away.
No, I know, I know that
our love will keep us steady.
Please. Will you speak to his father?
He'll listen to you if you
suggest him going to London.
Please.
I should find lodgings.
Be near the river,
close to the tanneries.
But I'm told that the currents
in the river are dangerous
and that you must engage
an experienced boatman
every time you cross, and I'll
be certain to do that every time,
I promise.
And I will think of you and Susanna
with every passing moment.
And I will find us lodgings in London,
and we shall all be together again.
Do you still not know
if it's a boy or a girl?
No.
Don't know why.
Have you not said that you
would always have two children?
Yes.
Two children at my deathbed.
Well, then, here is the second.
- We won't say goodbye.
- No.
You get-- Go.
- You going somewhere?
- No, I'm just...
Yes, I'm going to the lake...
You're not going to the forest.
- I must.
- No, you must not. Gilbert!
You... you have to let me go there.
- Let me go there!
- Listen Agnes.
- You must let me go!
- The river has burst its banks!
- Let me!
- There is no way...
- There's no way to get to the forest.
- Let me! No!
- We have everything ready for you.
- My baby!
No, my-my baby.
I can't.
It isn't coming out.
I will not have my baby in this house.
Not in this house.
No.
The river.
- Hush, hush, hush, hush. Hush.
- No, no, no, no.
He spoke about the river.
The river is dangerous. He
may be swept downstream!
Agnes. Agnes.
Agnes. Agnes, all is well with him.
Do you not recall his last letter?
Stop the screaming.
You'll wake the whole town.
He sound...
He sounded different.
No, he had good news for us.
- The theater.
- Theater.
He has a contract with the players
- to make gloves for the theater.
- the theater
Agnes, hush now.
Hush. Hush. Hush.
Bear down. Bear down.
Ah! Ooh!
- There we go.
- It's a boy.
There we go.
Good boy. Good boy.
It's a boy.
My boy.
Thank you.
What is it? What's happening?
She's starting again.
- You're having twins, my girl.
- Come on, Eliza.
Here. Quickly.
Take him.
No, no, no.
Two standing at my deathbed.
I always believed that it would be...
that they would be my children.
And now...
now I see it will be you.
We need to get you to the stool.
It's coming. It's here.
- No.
- Come on. Come on up. Up, up.
Please. I can't... I...
I can't.
- Go.
- I should never have...
I can't...
I can't make it.
I got it wrong. I got it wrong.
I got it...
He... He's not here.
He's... He's not here.
Agnes, you can...
and you must.
I cannot.
Agnes.
You can...
and you will.
Your husband was
born here in this room.
He took his first breath
there by the window.
Please.
Please let this child live.
Let this child live. Please.
Will you let him...
Let him come back
and be with his child.
Please.
Let him think kindly of me always.
Remember me.
Mama.
Mum?
Just too weak.
She was in too much pain.
I mean, poor woman.
She just got weaker and weaker.
I mean, that's just the
way of it sometimes.
She-she must have
known the end was nigh.
Best not speak of her to the children.
Safer with a different mother.
So young.
They may not remember her.
- Mum!
- Agnes. Agnes.
- Mama, no!
- No, no. Agnes.
Child. Child.
- Mummy, no!
- No, no, no. Ch-Ch-Ch-- No.
- No!
- No.
- No, let me see her!
- No, no!
- Let me see her!
- No!
No, Mama!
- Agnes.
- No!
Mum. I want, I want my mum.
I want my mum...
Oh! Here we go! It's a girl!
It's a girl. She's...
- It's... Wait.
- What?
Come on. Come on.
Why is she not crying?
She lives not.
Let me have her.
You should not look
upon her. It's bad luck.
Give her to me.
I'll make sure it gets a decent burial.
Give me my child!
My child.
Agnes, you have a baby boy.
Let me bring him to you,
and you may feed him.
The girl has gone to heaven.
She's not gone to heaven.
I made a vow the night my mother died.
I will go to your church,
but I shan't say a word there.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
You will live.
I will make sure nothing
ever takes you away.
I actually couldn't find it.
Hmm.
Here.
Perfect.
I found my hat.
Okay. Yes.
Okay, take that side. Take that side.
Yeah.
And put it around here.
Perfect.
- Ooh. Sorry.
- Let me help you.
It's down my face.
- I'm Hamnet.
- I'm Judith.
There will be no running in this house.
Conduct yourselves, please, as...
gentlewomen and gentlemen.
Where are you going?
Yeah. He's-he's coming. He's coming.
Hello.
We all know they've swapped clothes.
How long are we going
to pretend we don't?
We'll pretend for as long as
they think they're the same.
Hi.
Father, will you help me
with the Greek passage
from yesterday's lesson?
Hamnet, I thought
you'd already learnt it.
I didn't because I left
my primer at school.
Well, Hamnet,
you need to take
your studies seriously.
How do you expect to
improve if you're not...
Let me not then die ingloriously
and without struggle...
But let me first do some great thing
that shall be told among men hereafter.
You rascals.
- Did we trick you?
- Of course you did.
You swapped places
to hoodwink me again.
Susanna, come here.
Come here.
Now, do you remember the thing
we were going to do for your mother?
- Yeah.
- You remember? You ready to do it?
- Okay. Go outside quickly.
Go, go, go, go, go.
- Just step toward...
- Wait.
One st-- Come to your right. Step.
Step. One more.
- What.
- One more.
When shall we three meet again?
In thunder, lightning or in rain?
When hurly-burly's done,
when the battle's lost and won!
That will be ere at set of sun.
- Where the place?
- Upon the heath.
There to meet with Agnes.
I come, Graymalkin.
Paddock calls.
Anon!
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
Hover through the...
Well done!
That was amazing!
Dig it deep, and then you
move all of it to the side,
and then you put it down here.
Right? And then you get
the soil around the sides,
and then you pat it more.
And then you get bits like that.
And you rub it in your hands.
Whoa. And then back!
Do this.
And when you're doing this, circle.
Yeah, like that.
Ready?
Forward. And back.
Now, parry, parry, parry.
Good. Again.
Now, after that one, I'm gonna do this,
and you get out of the way.
Ready? Circle off. Spin your sword.
No.
Circle, spin your sword.
Now, come forward.
And go back.
One, two three.
Out of the way!
Very good. Again.
Judith, what's this one called?
- Thyme. Thyme.
- Rosemary.
-Thyme.
- Thyme. Thyme.
- I got it mixed up.
- That's okay.
This one...
- Now, that's rosemary.
- Yeah.
And what is rosemary for?
- Putting it in apples.
- Apples.
No. What is Rosemary's for?
- Remembering.
Remembering.
Now, you're to rub
all this in your hands.
You blow a little wish.
To wish him on his way.
Yeah? And it's your secret with him.
Did you see him?
Did you not see him in the sky?
All right, do it again.
Make another wish.
Look. Right up there.
Look, just there. Did you see him?
And he's got all your wishes
tucked in his little heart.
So any time that you
want to remember him,
you just have to go...
Where are you going?
Huh? I'm gonna catch you!
I'm gonna catch you!
Father?
Is all well?
Yes.
Listen, I want you to stay
away from your grandfather.
He'll not hit your sisters,
but it's you that I worry for,
and I need to know that you'll
be safe when I'm not here.
You're going back to London again?
Yes, tomorrow.
Tomorrow?
It's all right.
Will we go with you this time?
No, not yet.
Hey.
I'll miss you.
But I have to go, you understand? I...
I know.
I understand.
That's good.
'Cause I need you to look after
your mother and your sisters.
Will you do that?
Yes.
- Will you be brave?
- Yes.
Yes?
- Will you be brave?
- Yes.
Will you be brave?!
- Huh?!
- Yes! Yes, I'll be brave!
I'll be brave. I'll be brave.
I've looked at houses for us in London.
-Autumn is coming.
- Mm.
And the children will fall ill.
Judith, she's still not strong enough.
She often gets congestion in her chest.
And the air in London is...
We can't.
But one day soon, we will.
We will come to London with you.
No, you won't.
You'll never come.
You've waited for the
heat of summer to pass...
...the dryness of autumn,
the snow and the cold.
You do not believe that
Judith will ever survive London.
You'd do anything in your
power to keep that child alive.
Isn't that what a mother
is supposed to do?
Of course it is.
So...
...I've decided to look
for land outside Stratford.
That's where you should
live with the children.
- Thank you.
- Mm-hmm.
Ooh!
Where is she? Ah!
Hamnet. There he is.
Come here.
I love you. I love you. I love you.
All right. Love you.
- Come on.
- Love you.
Love you.
Oh.
All right. Come here.
- Remember what I told you, okay?
- Okay.
Good boy.
- Bye.
Hamnet?
Come on. Come here.
Show me your hand.
What? What do you see?
I see you.
Grown.
And very strong.
And I see you in London
working with your father.
- In the theater?
- Yes.
At the playhouse.
What will I be doing?
What do you wish to do, Hamnet?
I should be one of the
players with a sword.
A sword?
Yes.
And I shall clash it against
the sword of the other player.
Show me.
There'll be a terrible fight,
and everybody watching will
be frightened out of their wits.
And who will win?
I shall, of course.
Of course you shall.
Something has upset them.
What could it be?
The weather?
Something in the air, perhaps?
Best tell Joan to keep
the children inside today.
Judith?
Where are you?
Wake up!
The baker told me her cat had kittens.
We need to see them.
There's eight, Judith. Eight!
We need to hurry. It's going to rain.
Judith?
Jude?
What's wrong?
What's wrong, Judith?
Judith, answer me.
Judith, wake up.
Judith, please. Judith.
- What is it?
- It's Judith.
How long has she been like this?
Since I returned from school.
Oh, my God.
She's got it.
Hasn't she?
She's got the pestilence.
Hasn't she, Mama?
Go find your grandmother.
Bid her to come.
Now!
She's burning up.
We need, um, more water.
Make a bigger fire
and heat up more water.
- We need warm water.
- Eliza, fetch more water
and bring the Bellis from the kitchen.
A row of cinnamon.
Cinnamon, that's good
for drawing out the heat.
Pineweed or a rue. Thyme, yes.
You'll find them in the room.
- Mama. Yeah.
- The other table. The other side.
Yeah, Mama's here, my love.
Here, drink this. It's
rosemary and jelly.
All will be well, hmm?
All will be well.
Judith, stay with.
Mama's here. It's okay. Mama's here.
Rhubarb. We need rhubarb
to purge the stomach,
drive out the pestilence.
Can you go and fetch some?
Mama's here. It's okay.
Judith, we're all here.
Susanna, draw some water, too.
Hamnet and... and Mary and Susanna.
Draw water as soon as you can.
Why isn't he here?
Eliza, go write to your
brother and tell him to come.
Judith.
Open your mouth, Judith.
Open your mouth.
Mama's here. That's it.
That's good.
Yes, you'll be safe.
You'll open your mouth. Drink it down.
Swallow it down. Mama's
here. It's okay, Judith.
Mama's here. It's okay.
Okay.
Agnes.
You have done all that you can.
I will not let her cross over.
Grandmama, you had three
daughters that were taken.
Were they...
Were they like Judith?
Anne was seven.
The other two were just babies.
They all had swellings and...
...fever like Judith.
Your mother's trying to...
keep a grip on her child.
It won't work.
What is given may be
taken away at any time.
We must never let our guard down.
Never take for granted...
...that our children's hearts beat,
that they draw breath,
that they walk and speak and...
...smile, argue, play.
Never forget for a moment
that they may be gone.
Jude.
Don't be sad.
You shall be well.
I shall not.
Not without you.
It's here.
Do you see it, Jude?
It's watching us.
I'll tell it to take us both.
We'll go together.
Turn away.
It'll make a mistake.
It can't tell us apart.
Breathe with me, Judith.
I give you my life.
You shall be well.
I give you my life, Judith.
I'll be brave.
I'll be brave, Father.
Whoa.
Quick as you can.
Hamnet.
Hamnet, you're not
supposed to be down here.
I need to take you up to bed.
Hamnet.
Hamnet?
Mama.
Hamnet.
You must open your mouth.
All will be well.
He's burning.
He's burning up.
It will not sti-- It will not stick!
A stone. There's a stone.
There's a stone upstairs
with a hole in the middle of it.
By his bedside.
Bring it down. I need it.
And, um, uh, salt. Get salt.
Get it. Can you give it?
Can you f-fetch me some
salt, as much salt as you have.
Water. We need water.
He's... he's too hot.
He's burning.
My love. Mama's here.
All will be well. All will be well.
All will be well.
Hamnet, don't be scared.
No need to be scared.
All will be well. Mommy's here.
Mommy's here. It's okay.
Mommy's here.
Look at me. Mommy's here.
I will never, ever let you go.
You understand?
I love you.
Eliza, take Judith to the
kitchen and keep her there.
Please!
- He needs me!
- Stay there.
He needs me!
Please!
Valerian...
Hamnet. Hamnet. Hamnet.
Hamnet, you have to
stay. Hamnet, please.
Hamnet, please. You
have to stay with us.
Mama needs you. We need you.
- Stop! Enough!
- Stay with us. Stay, stay.
Please, Hamnet. Hamnet, Hamnet, Hamnet.
- Let him alone!
- Hamnet, please!
Can't you see that
it's too late for him!
Please, please.
Hamnet?
Hamnet. Hamnet. Please. Hamnet.
My son is gone.
Just so bereft... it's my son.
I've lost my...
I saw the light, and I couldn't sleep.
Here.
Oh, child, no.
- No, no, no. Go to bed.
- No, no, let-let her stay.
It is my fault, Mama. It is my fault.
No. No.
It is not your fault, Judith.
But he changed places with me.
He tricked it.
He tricked what?
Death.
Judith.
It took him when it came for me.
Never say those words
to anyone ever again.
The fever came for your
brother, and it took him.
Do you wish to see him?
Yes.
Go on. You can see him.
Is it really him?
Yes.
It-it doesn't look like him.
No.
It's not him.
It's not.
It-It's-it's not morning yet.
We haven't prepared him properly.
Am I too late?
- It's you.
- Father.
It's you.
It's me.
Where is he?
Where is...
Where...
It's my boy.
I didn't see it.
I should've paid him more attention.
I always thought she was
the one to be taken away
when all the while it was him.
I'm a fool.
No, there's nothing anyone
could have done to save him.
You did everything that you could.
Of course I did.
You weren't here.
I would have cut my heart
out and given it to him.
I would have laid my life
down on the ground for him.
- I-I know. I know.
- And no one would take it.
- But you...
- No, you don't know.
You don't know. You weren't here.
He died in agony.
I...
- He was in agony.
- Agnes.
He cried and he cried
- and he cried and he cried.
- Agnes, stop, stop.
- And his little body was wracked in pain.
- Shh.
No, don't shush me.
He was so scared.
- And you weren't here.
- I know.
I tried everything I could.
I know you did.
- I tried everything I could.
- You did everything that you could.
You did everything that you could.
Everything.
Agnes. Agnes.
I will send word, Agnes.
You'll send word?
- To whom?
- To you.
I'm here.
What I meant was that I shall
send word when I reach London.
London?
I must leave.
Leave? How can you leave?
The world does simply
not stand still, Agnes.
There are people
waiting for me in London.
The season is about to begin,
and my company shall
return from Kent any day now.
I have to go now.
Now?
There's a traveling
party leaving today,
and they have a spare horse, so yeah.
Look after the girls,
and I will return to--
Stop.
Don't.
Go. Go.
"When I do count the
clock that tells the time,
"And see the brave day
sunk in hideous night;
"When I behold the violet past prime,
"And sable curls all
silver'd o'er with white;
"When lofty trees I
see barren of leaves
"Which erst from the
heat did canopy the herd,
"And summer's green
all girded up in sheaves
"Borne on the bier with
white and bristly beard;
"Then of thy beauty do I question make,
"Thou among the wastes of time must go,
"Since sweets and beauties
do themselves forsake
"And die as fast as
they see others grow;
"And nothing gainst time's
scythe can make defense
Save breed, to brave him
when he takes thee hence."
Will you read it again?
No.
I've read it three times.
That's enough.
- Shall we do presents?
- Presents? from London?
A hair comb for you, Jude.
Mind you, you'll have to be careful.
This is for you, Agnes.
- A ruby, is it?
- Mm-hmm.
It's the finest I've ever seen.
Everyone's talking about the new house.
It's the biggest in Stratford.
There are so many
rooms. One could get lost.
You shall keep the keys, Susanna.
You shall manage the house well.
Put it on, Mama.
Did Bartholomew show you the new house?
Mm-hmm.
Do you like it?
Why didn't you show me yourself?
Were you afraid I wouldn't leave?
'Cause Hamnet died here in this house.
You know, I'm constantly
wondering where he is.
Or where he has gone.
Whatever I'm doing, I'm
wondering, "Where is he?"
I mean, he can't have just vanished.
All he needs is for me to find him.
He must be somewhere.
I fear I may run mad with
it, even now, a year on.
A year is nothing.
A year is nothing. It's every second...
every minute, every day.
We may never stop looking for him.
I'm sorry, Agnes.
Did you hear me? I
said that I'm sorry, Agnes.
- For what?
- For everything.
- You're caught by that place.
- For...
- What place?
- That place in your head.
It is now more real to
you than anywhere else.
Not even the death of our
child can keep you from it.
Hamnet died.
A horrible death.
And you should have been there.
You could have bid him farewell.
What do you see?
Hmm?
Nothing.
Nothing?
Nothing at all.
Oh, well.
You should go back to London.
You need not concern yourself with us.
Get along just fine without you.
This was sometime a paradox,
but now the time gives it proof.
I did love you once.
Indeed, my lord, you
made me believe so.
You should not have believed me,
for virtue cannot so
inoculate our old stock for...
You should not have believed me,
for virtue cannot so
inoculate our old stock
but we shall relish of it.
I loved you not.
I was the more deceived.
Get thee to a nunnery.
Why wouldst thou be
a breeder of sinners?
I am myself indifferent honest,
but yet I could accuse
me of such things
that it were better to...
Again.
Get thee to a nunnery.
Why wouldst thou be
a breeder of sinners?
I am myself indifferent honest, but...
Again. "I am myself
indifferent honest." Again.
I am myself indifferent honest,
but yet I could accuse me of
such things that it were better
- my mother had not borne me.
- Again.
I, myself...
- And...
- Again.
I, myself, am indifferent...
"I am myself."
I am myself indifferent honest,
but yet I could accuse me
of such things that it were...
Again.
But yet I could accuse me
of such things that it were...
Again!
I am myself indifferent honest,
but yet I could accuse me of such...
You are simply mouthing the words!
I am myself indifferent honest,
but yet I could accuse
me of such things
that it were better my
mother had not borne me.
I am very proud, revengeful, ambitious,
with more offenses at my beck
than I have thoughts to put them in,
imagination to give them
shape or time to act them in.
Now, what should such fellows as I do
crawling between heaven and earth?
We are arrant knaves all.
Believe none of us.
Go thy ways to a nunnery. Again.
To be...
...or not to be...
...that is the question:
Whether 'tis nobler
in the mind to... suffer
The slings and arrows of...
...outrageous fortune...
...Or...
...to take arms against a...
...sea of troubles,
And by opposing...
...end them.
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ For ♪
♪ Sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
Agnes?
I... I was in town, and I...
I thought I would pay you a visit.
I was very sorry to hear
about John's passing.
How's your husband?
It's a... it's a terrible
thing to lose one's father.
He's well.
He's very busy. He's
preparing a comedy.
His new play is not a comedy.
It's a tragedy.
But you knew that.
Everyone in town is talking about it.
I did warn you about marrying him...
Don't pretend that you care for me.
You are not my mother,
and you never were.
Good day, Agnes.
He's not spoken to us for months.
How could he...
How could he not tell us?
Do you not wonder what is in it?
In what?
The play.
Who are you looking for?
William Shakespeare.
We're his family from Stratford.
Go up the stairs.
He lives in the attic.
Why would the man with
the largest house in Stratford
be living here?
I don't understand.
I thought...
I thought he...
What shall I do?
Keep your heart open.
(All the world is a playhouse.)
- Who's there?
- Nay, answer me:
stand and unfold yourself!
Long live the king!
Bernardo?
If you do meet Horatio and Marcellus,
The rivals to my watch,
bid them make haste.
I think I hear them. Stand, ho!
Who's there?
Has this thing appeared again tonight?
- I have seen nothing.
- Horatio says...
What are they talking about?
...'tis but our fantasy...
...and will not let belief
take hold of him touching...
What has any of this to do with my son?
...this dreaded sight
twice seen of us...
These men are frightened.
Of what?
And let us once again
assail your ears...
They watch for a ghost.
...when yond same star
that's westward from the pole...
Ghost?
...The bell then beating one...
Peace; break thee off!
Look where it comes again!
In the same figure,
like the king that's dead.
See, it stalks away!
That was him.
...Tell me why this same...
- That was Will.
- Shh.
- He's not in the play.
- No, no.
It was Will as a ghost.
Our last king, Whose image
but now appeared to us,
Was dared to the combat;
our valiant Hamlet...
Hamlet.
Did you hear... did you hear that?
Yes.
They said his-- they said his name.
Agnes.
- Agnes, wait.
- Out of my way!
Please be quiet.
Wait, did they say his name? Huh?
Do not upset yourself.
Why is-- Why did he use his name?
- I don't know him.
- Quiet.
...and by my advice,
Let us impart what we have seen tonight
Unto the young prince...
Don't you dare pronounce my son's name!
Quiet!
...dumb to us, will speak to him.
Though yet of our dear brother's death,
The memory be green,
Yet so far hath discretion
fought with nature
That we with wisest
sorrow think on him,
Together with remembrance of ourselves.
I will not stay a minute
longer to be a part of this jest.
- Wait. One moment.
- ...my cousin.
- No. I want to go home.
- Hamlet...
and my son...
How is it that the
clouds still hang on you?
Good Hamlet, cast
thy nighted color off.
Do not for ever with thy vailed lids
Seek for thy noble father in the dust.
All that lives must die,
Passing through nature to eternity.
Ay, madam, it is common.
But I have that within
which passes show.
These are but the trappings
and the suits of woe.
To persevere In obstinate condolement
is a course of impious stubbornness.
'Tis unmanly grief.
It shows a will most
incorrect to heaven.
Oh.
This too, too solid flesh would melt,
Thaw and resolve itself into a dew.
Or that the Everlasting had not fixed
His canon gainst self-slaughter.
'Tis an unweeded
garden That grows to seed;
things rank and gross in
nature possess it merely.
That it should come to this.
But two months dead--
nay, not so much, not two--
So excellent a king, that was to this
Hyperion to a... a satyr.
Whither wilt thou lead me?
Speak. I'll go no further.
I am thy father's spirit,
Doomed for a certain
term to walk the night,
And for the day
confined to fast in fires.
My hour is almost come
When I to sulfurous
and tormenting flames
Must render up myself.
- Alas, poor ghost.
- No, pity me not...
...but lend thy serious
hearing to what I shall unfold.
List.
List, oh, list.
If thou didst ever thy father love...
Oh, God.
But soft, methinks I
scent the morning air.
Brief let me be. Sleeping
within my orchard.
Upon my secure hour, thy uncle stole
With juice of cursed hebona in a vile,
Within the porches of my ears did pour
The leprous distillment...
...whose effect Holds such
an enmity with blood of man
That swift as quicksilver
it courses through
The natural gates
and alleys of the body.
And with a sudden vigor it doth posset
And curd, like...
...eager droppings into milk,
The thin and wholesome blood.
So did it mine.
A most instant tetter barked about...
...Most lazar-like, with
vile and loathsome crust,
All my smooth body.
Oh.
Horrible.
Oh, horrible. Most horrible.
If thou hast nature
in thee, bear it not...
He has swapped places with our son.
Look at me.
The... the glowworm
shows the matin to be near,
And 'gins to pale
his uneffectual fires.
My boy.
Adieu.
Remember me.
To be, or not to be,
that is the question.
Whether 'tis nobler
in the mind to suffer
The slings and arrows
of outrageous fortune,
Or to take arms
against a sea of troubles
And, by opposing, end them.
To die, to sleep,
No more.
And by a sleep, to say we end
The heartache and the
thousand natural shocks
That flesh is heir to--
'tis a consummation
Devoutly to be wished.
To die,
To sleep, perchance to dream.
Ay, there's the rub.
For in that sleep of death,
what dreams may come
When we have shuffled
off this mortal coil
Must give us pause.
There's the respect
That makes calamity of so long life.
Who would bear the
whips and scorns of time,
The oppressor's wrong,
the proud man's contumely,
The pangs of despised love,
the law's delay,
The insolence of office, and the spurns
That patient merit
of the unworthy take,
When he himself might his quietus make
With a bare bodkin?
Who would fardels bear,
To grunt and sweat under a weary life,
But that the dread of
something after death,
The undiscovered
country from whose bourn
No traveler returns, puzzles the will,
And makes us rather bear those ills...
En garde!
One!
No! No!
A hit, a palpable hit!
Our son shall win!
- Well, again!
- Gertrude, do not drink.
Another hit! What say you?
Have at you now!
How does the queen?
She swoons to see them bleed.
No, no, the drink, the drink!
Oh, my dear Hamlet.
I am poisoned.
Oh, villainy!
Ho, let the door be locked!
Treachery! Seek it out!
It is here, Hamlet.
Hamlet, thou art slain.
No medicine in the
world can do thee good.
In thee, there is not
half an hour's life.
The king's to blame!
The point envenomed, too?
Then, venom, to thy work!
Here, thou incestuous,
murderous, damned Dane!
Drink...
Drink off this potion!
Is thy union here?
Follow my mother.
I am dead.
Thou livest.
Report me and my cause aright
To the unsatisfied.
If thou didst ever
hold me in thy heart,
Absent thee from felicity awhile,
And in this harsh world
draw thy breath in pain
To tell my story.
Ah, I die!
The potent poison
quite o'ercrows my spirit.
The rest is silence.
Subtitles by MontageSubs
♪ My Robin to the greenwood will go ♪
♪ Where the oak and the ash ♪
♪ And the briars do grow ♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ The greenwood is near ♪
♪ And the greenwood is far ♪
♪ And many a danger ♪
♪ Befalls a man there ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ Is all my joy ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
MontageSubs (蒙太奇字幕组)
Powered by Love ♥ 用爱发电